<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Job | With Pith]]></title>
  <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/blog/categories/job/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-19T16:09:29-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://ethanp.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ethan Petuchowski]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning vs Doing]]></title>
    <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/12/19/learning-vs-doing/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-19T16:05:20-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/12/19/learning-vs-doing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The goal of my first project at my first &ldquo;real&rdquo; job is to get something useful
done within a few days and start to feel like a contributing member of the
team. However it has been about a week, and I still have not finished that
project.</p>

<p>From my experience talking with some of my colleagues so far, their collective
attitude might be summed up with, &ldquo;Google it, then copy-paste it, but don&rsquo;t
worry about what it does.&rdquo; In my life, I have worked with and met <em>many</em> people
having that attitude. Partially because of my experience working with those
people, it happens to decidedly <em>not</em> be <em>my</em> attitude. My attitude is more
like &ldquo;google it, learn what to do, learn why that is the right approach, take
notes, and then copy-paste and modify the best solution to make the final
solution as clean as possible.&rdquo; This strategy got me through many tough
situations, so I have built up faith in it.</p>

<p>So, after seeing me spend <em>days</em> learning about ssh tunnelling, ansible, and
vagrant &mdash; and not finishing my simple project &mdash; they finally said something
along the lines of</p>

<blockquote><p>At this rate it will take you weeks to learn how to automate deployment of a
virtual machine. Why don&rsquo;t you just deploy <em>one</em> copy and then learn about
how to automate it on your <em>own</em> time?</p></blockquote>

<p>Now, &ldquo;weeks&rdquo; is probably an overstatement, but they pointed out to me that I
had sort of assumed out of nowhere that I was hired as some sort of devops role
for the company, even though what I&rsquo;m actually interested in is what one might
call &ldquo;big data engineering&rdquo;. They said, &ldquo;<em>If</em> you find yourself repeating the
same tasks over and over, <em>then</em> you should learn to automate them.&rdquo; It is now
obvious that they are in the right.</p>

<p>At the time, I was startled by the way they approached me about what I consider
to be largely a difference in personalities. But I can see that they are
concerned that someone who reads too much never gets anything done, and so far
I have fit that stereotype. At the same time, I am concerned that a person who
<em>doesn&rsquo;t</em> read will do their work quickly and incorrectly and will then spend
the next few weeks rejiggering a broken project, and so far they have fit that
stereotype. In short, it seems that we are all prejudiced and have plenty to
learn from each other.</p>

<p>Going forward I shall take their advice and do the more mundane tasks as fast
as possible and only learn things that come up more than once. If that doesn&rsquo;t
work out for me because I&rsquo;m just cranking out shitty work, I will revert back
to understanding what I am doing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
