<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: School | With Pith]]></title>
  <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/blog/categories/school/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-06T15:14:08-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://ethanp.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ethan Petuchowski]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Asking for Advice]]></title>
    <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2016/02/27/asking-for-advice/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-27T15:38:06-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2016/02/27/asking-for-advice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are many circumstances in life during which one may feel the need to ask
for advice. For example, when evaluating a significant decision, or when
dealing with an emotionally stressful circumstance. Here, I will discuss
advice about significant decisions.</p>

<p>In giving advice, everyone has a different approach. I generally try to follow
a line I heard in a rap song by The Streets, &ldquo;If you never tell a lie to her,
you don&rsquo;t have to remember anything.&rdquo; In other words, lying will only
complicate your life because you have to remember the lies you made up.
(Caveat: this may not always the best way to go for emotionally complex
issues.) I also enjoy helping people rationally and realistically evaluate
their options for significant decisions, and surely if someone recalls that
your input was helpful in the past, they will be more likely to ask you in the
future.</p>

<p>Most people I know don&rsquo;t seem to like giving useful advice. It seems they
either are (1) too afraid that their honesty will lead you to dislike them, or
(2) they feel so stressed with their own issues that taking on yours for a few
minutes would be overwhelming, or (3) they find your problem uninteresting and
simply have better things to do.</p>

<p>But some people are the opposite. They will patiently listen to your question
and give what they feel to be an honest evaluation of where you stand and what
you should do. The advice of people in this category will often be heavily and
obviously biased by their own experience and ideology. This is simply a
symptom of &ldquo;being honest&rdquo;.</p>

<p>So if you want good advice, it would be ideal to find someone who is honest,
not stressed about a similar problem to yours, as well as interested in and
knowledgeable of the subject; they should generally also be disinterested in
your particular problem. However, this ideal candidate is not always
available.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In that case one can obviously try the timeless &ldquo;pros vs cons&rdquo; list, which
doesn&rsquo;t necessarily rely on external sources of wisdom, but often external
sources of wisdom are critical. One can ask unideal candidates for advice, and
maybe they&rsquo;ll at least have some curt nugget that has some use. That&rsquo;s what I
usually do, and it is generally not effective at all, but occasionaly that
curt nugget is exactly the required pithy jewel.</p>

<p>One can consult the Internet, but I kind of assumed that if you needed advice,
you already checked the Internet for answers. But to go one step further you
can <em>ask</em> the Internet, treating it like this all knowing Oracle. This will
work to varying degrees depending on your problem. If your problem is one that
everyone and their mother has an opinion on, you will end up sifting through
junk answers, and may or may not get anything useful. In that case, the more
details you can reveal, the more benefit you will obtain. Of course <em>where</em>
you ask matters: for example Quora will be more effective than Yahoo Answers.
If your problem is esoteric, <em>find the people who are into that thing</em>.</p>

<p>For example, I have noticed to my surprise that StackOverflow/StackExchange is
not always the best place for all programming-related questions, because if
your question is esoteric to one technological ecosystem, the question-
answering population on StackOverflow won&rsquo;t necessarily have the flag-bearers
of the cause of that particular ecosystem. But if it really is an ecosystem,
it will have a place where the flag-bearers dwell, so <em>find it</em> and they will
probably help. In my experience, IRC channels tend to be empty; Gitter
channels may be well-attended; Github issues get a lot of flak for being a
mess, but are often effective if you&rsquo;re sure your question isn&rsquo;t stupid;
mailing lists can be high-latency but that&rsquo;s often where the true experts of
super-technical projects converse. Following <strong>good forum-question-asking
practices</strong> is <em>crucial</em> in <em>any</em> of these environments, and it can be
trickier to do that than it sounds. <strong>The better you phrase your question, the
more appealing it is to answer in the eyes of a high-quality potential source
of advice.</strong></p>

<p>Sometimes the advice you receive from multiple sources will be in direct
conflict with each other. I have been having this issue a lot lately. Let&rsquo;s
say one person suggested I do <code>A</code>, and another suggested I do <code>not A</code>. I have
decided this pair of suggestions implies that <em>either</em> decision is just fine,
which is basically the ideal outcome; viz. my so-called &ldquo;significant decision&rdquo;
was not so significant after all and doesn&rsquo;t not need to be balanced
carefully.</p>

<p>Just some biased thoughts from my experience; take some, leave some, etc.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why the WiFi Sucks on the Porch]]></title>
    <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/09/24/why-the-wifi-sucks-on-the-porch/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-24T14:31:30-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/09/24/why-the-wifi-sucks-on-the-porch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Why is WiFi so slow on the porch?</h2>

<p>The problem at my house is that WiFi connectivity is generally fine inside the
house, but while sitting on the porch it is nearly impossible for anyone to
browse the Hinternets. I think a lesson of my <a href="http://www.cs.utexas.edu/~lili/classes/F15-CS386W/">Wireless Networking</a> course
explains this observation.</p>

<p>In Wireless networking we have the situation called the <a href="http://www.wikiwand.com/en/Hidden_node_problem"><strong>Hidden Terminal
Problem</strong></a>, which is the following. Node <code>A</code> is too far from node <code>C</code> to
hear its transmissions, but both are in range of node <code>B</code> which sits between
<code>A</code> and <code>C</code>. Suppose <code>C</code> is currently transmitting data to <code>B</code>. Now <code>A</code> checks
whether any transmissions are currently happening, and finds that there are
none (because it is out of range of <code>C</code>). So <code>A</code> goes ahead and sends data to
<code>B</code>. Now <code>B</code> can&rsquo;t understand either data packet because they collided and
interfered with each other in an unrecoverable way because they were both sent
in the same channel.</p>

<p>I think the porch scenario is simply an example of the <em>Hidden Terminal
Problem</em> above. In my room, my laptop can hear many of my neighbors' WiFi LAN
networks, but it&rsquo;s the same set that my WiFi router sitting in the closet can
hear. However outside, where there&rsquo;s less cause for signal attenuation, my
laptop can hear many more WiFi LAN networks than the router inside. So the
router checks whether there is congestion, doesn&rsquo;t hear any, and sends the
data. But there <em>is</em>, in fact, congestion, and my computer doesn&rsquo;t receive the
data properly. The data is therefore not <em>ACKd</em>, the router times out on the
<em>ACK</em>, and has to retransmit, and so on. This makes for a <em>far</em> slower
Hinterconnectivity outside on the porch than in my room.</p>

<p>Maybe the lesson learnt is that the WiFi router should be situated in a place
where it can hear more of the outside noise so that it can compensate better
for that noise.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Basics of Wireless Communication]]></title>
    <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/09/07/basics-of-wireless-communication/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-07T15:45:58-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/09/07/basics-of-wireless-communication</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been doing the readings for my <a href="http://www.cs.utexas.edu/~lili/classes/F15-CS386W/">Wireless Networking course</a> at
UTexas, and in the process have dug into much of the basics of radios and
networks that I had ignored in the past. Here, I will try briefly describe what
I have learned. Maybe not everything I will say here is exactly correct, but I
think it&rsquo;s at least <em>mostly</em> correct.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s try to start somewhere near the beginning. Our <strong>goal</strong> is to transfer a
<em>information</em> from one location <code>LocSND</code> to another <code>LocRCV</code> <em>conveniently</em>.
The way we will accomplish that is by having <code>LocSND</code> manipulate the
<em>electromagnetic field</em> around <code>LocRCV</code>. More specifically, we will <em>encode</em> a
binary <em>dataframe</em> as <em>modulations</em> of a <em>radio signal</em> around a pre-determined
<em>carrier frequency</em>.</p>

<p>How do we <em>do</em> that?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>We use an LRC circuit to make electrons oscillate in an
antenna. These oscillating electrons ram into loose and excitable electrons in
the antenna&rsquo;s metal, this releases a photon at a particular frequency. Globally
(i.e. within the entire transmitting antenna), enough photons are being
released that it seems to an external observer looking at the produced
electromagnetic (EM) field like there is a continuous signal being emitted.</p>

<p>So we&rsquo;re sending these EM ripples, which are generally at our carrier
frequency. However, if we just sent a basic frequency, there would be no
<em>information</em> in there, so we have to <em>modulate</em> it. We can modulate its
amplitude (A), phase (phi), and frequency (omega), the 3 free
parameters of the equation (in the top left of the equation in the following
gif from &ldquo;sengpielaudio&rdquo;)</p>

<p><img src="http://www.sengpielaudio.com/Sinuskurve01.gif" alt="sine wave" /></p>

<p>This would give us
1. <strong>Carrier frequency</strong> &mdash;&ndash; the EM frequency <em>inside</em> which our signal is
  encoded
2. <strong>amplitude shift keying (ASK)</strong> &mdash; send signal at <em>carrier frequency</em> by
   modulating the signal&rsquo;s <em>amplitude</em>
3. <strong>frequency shift keying (FSK)</strong> &mdash; similar but modulates <em>frequency</em>
4. <strong>phase shift keying (PSK)</strong> &mdash; again, but modulates <em>phase</em></p>

<p>One simple method would be to say our carrier frequency is 5 Hz, but our band
is actually [4,6] Hz. So whenever the signal is 4 Hz, that means I&rsquo;m sending a
0, and if the signal is 6 Hz, it means I&rsquo;m sending a 1, and a new digit starts
every 1 ms. That would be an example of <strong>FSK</strong>.</p>

<p>A fundamental problem that we must solve is that all senders and receivers of
information via EM fields with their antenna(s) are sharing the a single
<em>medium</em> for transmitting that field (viz. the air, etc.). So if <code>LocSND</code> sends
a message to <code>LocRCV_1</code>, then <code>LocRCV_2</code> sitting one foot away can hear that
message loud and clear. This leads to three major issues: <strong>security</strong>,
<strong>multiplexing</strong>, and <strong>interference</strong>.</p>

<p>To <strong>multiplex</strong> means to send multiple distinct signals through a single
channel. How are we going to send distinct signals to receivers 1 and 2 in such
a way that both can understand the signal meant for them? We can chop up the
frequency band that our transmitter can use into 2 smaller bands, and use each
of those bands as separate carriers. Then we tune the receivers to pick up
frequencies in their respective bands. This is what is called <strong>frequency
division multiplexing (FDM)</strong>, but we can also multiplex across space, time,
and <em>code</em>.</p>

<p>Of course, I&rsquo;ve only scratched the very surface of what&rsquo;s going on here, but
that&rsquo;s all the time I&rsquo;ve got.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simulating a Distributed System]]></title>
    <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/05/18/simulating-a-distributed-system/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-18T17:24:37-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/05/18/simulating-a-distributed-system</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For my Distributed Computing class at school, there were 3 projects that each
involved implementing a distributed protocol over a simulated distributed
cluster of computers that are only &lsquo;connected&rsquo; to one another in that they know
each other&rsquo;s IP address and must communicate over TCP sockets. For each of the
3 projects, I had a <em>completely</em> different method of implementing the system.</p>

<h3>Implementation One: A True Distributed System in Vanilla Java</h3>

<p>The first project (Three Phase Commit) was the only one for which I worked with
a partner. We were unclear how to attack the problem of building a distributed
system in a simple way, so we went ahead and implemented a truly distributable
Java application, in which you could spin up processes on any computer and it
would connect in to the master server, who would tell the new node the
listening ports of other servers in the cluster manually, etc. This turned out
to be perhaps overly ambitious. When a node was expecting a message from
someone else, it would fire a timer thread, which on completion would report to
the master to restart the failed process. This system did work properly
(somehow) but it seemed to be living-on-the-edge. It also required two weeks of
a lot of working on it and learning aspects of Java, unit testing, mocks, which
<code>Exception</code> would get thrown by which network event &amp; when, etc.</p>

<h3>Implementation Two: Lightweight System Simulation</h3>

<p>For the second project (Paxos), I said &ldquo;Hooey&rdquo; to all the Java hubbub, which
while I enjoyed its low-level-ness, forcing me to peak further under the hood,
it required a larger time commitment than I was prepared to make. I realized
that my class&rsquo;s requirements only specified that system &ldquo;nodes&rdquo; run
concurrently, share no memory, and talk over TCP. So in Scala, I made a <code>Node</code>
class state machine, and ran different instances of it on separate threads.
This was too easy though, and I was disappointed to find my implementation
complete more than two weeks before the due date.</p>

<h3>Implementation Three: Akka Cluster</h3>

<p>Akka Cluster is a Scala-based framework for building a distributed system, in
which you define the address of a set of &ldquo;seed&rdquo; nodes, of whom at least one is
supposed be available at all times. Then when other nodes start up, they become
a &ldquo;member&rdquo; of the cluster by contacting any seed node. So for me (the &ldquo;client&rdquo;
of Akka Cluster), all there is left to do is define the protocol to run on top
of the cluster. (In this case the protocol was the simple eventually-consistent
database protocol &ldquo;Bayou&rdquo;.)</p>

<p>Akka nodes follow the &ldquo;Actor Model&rdquo;, meaning they share no state with any other
part of your program, making them &ldquo;simple&rdquo; to run on remote machines (I didn&rsquo;t
try that, the docs say it is easy though). The only way actors can communicate
is via message passing, for which there is a dedicated syntax, <code>!</code>. For
example:</p>

<p><code>scala
case class MyMessage(data: DataElem)
anotherActor ! MyMessage(theData)
</code></p>

<p>The code above would have the actor running this code, send <code>anotherActor</code> an
instance of the case class <code>MyMessage</code> with the <code>DataElem</code> that was passed in.</p>

<p>Inter-actor communcation is guaranteed <em>FIFO</em> by Akka, meaning that for any
pair of actors <code>A, B</code>, if <code>A</code> sends <code>n</code> messages to <code>B</code>, <code>B</code> will receive those
messages in the same order that <code>A</code> sent them. NB this says nothing about the
order with respect to other actors in the system.</p>

<p>Using Akka trivialized all sorts of implementation details I&rsquo;d had to worry
about in the first project, and then ignored for the second project.</p>

<p>If there had been a 4th project for this class, it&rsquo;s clear to me that I would
use Akka again. For some reason my code ran <em>very</em> slowly, and it probably had
to do with some configuration-setting that I did not set in the Akka config
file. That was really the only problem I had that I did not fix. One problem I
did fix that took a while, was figuring out a good way to shut the system down.
There were various options discussed online, and eventually I found one that
worked for me, which was to call <code>system.shutdown()</code> on every instance System I
instantiate. Another option was to send <code>self ! PoisonPill</code> but for some reason
that didn&rsquo;t work. I guess different ones work for different situations.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Asynchronous System]]></title>
    <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/05/03/asynchronous-system/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-03T19:27:36-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/05/03/asynchronous-system</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before taking a Distributed Computing course at school, I had written for
various program environments:</p>

<ol>
<li>a script that trains a neural network to recognize whether an English
sentence is grammatical</li>
<li>an iOS app that involves a fair bit of multi-threading</li>
<li>a command line interpreter that forks and runs commands as background
processes</li>
<li>the Raft distributed consensus protocol inside a professor’s multi-threaded
distributed system simulator</li>
<li>some asynchronous features for a simplified database system where threads
communicate solely via Java’s <code>PipedInputStreams</code> instead of using shared
variables</li>
</ol>


<p>Perhaps you are familiar with these situations, and like me thought they might
be “distributed”. Reality check: they’re not. Similarly, in a distributed
system, one has multiple “threads” processing data at once. However,
these “threads” may be each on different machines; this adds some complexity.
None of the situations outlined above have the sort of issues one can expect
fairly regularly when talking amongst machines.</p>

<h3>Different machines don’t share</h3>

<!-- more -->


<ol>
<li>heap space</li>
<li>scheduler</li>
<li>clock time (i.e. at any moment each machine&rsquo;s &ldquo;watch&rdquo; reads a different
time)</li>
<li>clock tick speed (i.e. clock time&rsquo;s &ldquo;drift&rdquo; apart from one another)</li>
<li>stable storage</li>
<li>etc.</li>
</ol>


<h3>They can’t differentiate between friends in any of the following states</h3>

<ol>
<li>dead</li>
<li>became slow</li>
<li>the network literally broke down between the two</li>
<li>the network become slow between the two</li>
</ol>


<p>This is because all they know is &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve sent my buddy a message and have yet to
hear back.&rdquo;</p>

<h2>If you told me all this, my response might be:</h2>

<blockquote><p>Why not just run your program under the expectation things will work, and
hope for the best?</p></blockquote>

<h3>The answer (as far as I can guess) is several fold:</h3>

<ol>
<li>“If you are the company who has figured out a better answer than ‘hoping
for the best,’ people will pay you for access to your software” &mdash; Adam
Smith</li>
<li>Your Users will be <em>very</em> pissed if their stuff seems to randomly
disappear; even if it only happens to a few of them every once in a while.

<ul>
<li>This becomes especially likely if you have a lot of users with a lot of
data</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>You’re going to have to be super-over-cautious about not losing important
data. It would be great to speed things up in such a way that you&rsquo;re still
not losing any important data, but also not wasting time being overly
cautious.</li>
</ol>


<p>For the research community, the method they have derived for coming up with
better solutions than the never-failing “hope for the best,” is <strong>formalism</strong>.
By giving ideas with a lot of moving parts names, they simplify the task of
using the human brain to derive solutions. The most important formalism is the
<strong>asynchronous model</strong>.</p>

<h2>The Setting: Asynchronous Message-Passing and Assumptions</h2>

<p>In an <strong>asynchronous system</strong> (as opposed to a <em>synchronous</em> one), a few
properties of the system are explicitly assumed. The basic assumptions are
listed above under the names <strong>“Different machines don’t share”</strong> and <strong>“They
can’t differentiate between when each another machine has done any of the
following”</strong>.</p>

<p>However, in an effort to always find the simplest solution under the smallest
set of assumptions possible, different authors use variations on the above
assumptions. Commonly they will say something like &ldquo;channels are reliable&rdquo;, by
which they mean the network connection between any two nodes will always
<em>eventually</em> transmit every message it is asked to. The word <em>eventually</em> is
thrown around a lot, and it means there is some time before <em>never</em> when it
will happen.</p>

<p>By adding additional assumptions (e.g. &ldquo;packets sent between any pair of
processes cannot be reordered en route&rdquo;) simpler solutions can often be found.
By removing assumptions, upper bounds can be established on the costs of
solving certain problems.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
