<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Taxes | With Pith]]></title>
  <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/blog/categories/taxes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-09T15:06:33-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://ethanp.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ethan Petuchowski]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Tone Makes the Point]]></title>
    <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2016/01/07/the-tone-makes-the-point/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-07T08:40:04-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2016/01/07/the-tone-makes-the-point</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, hot-shot investor Paul Graham wrote a <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/ineq.html">piece about economic
inequality</a>. This essay provoked a lot of dialogue online. I read the
piece, and a few responses to it. I enjoyed the essay, and I found it very
persuasive. In fact, I would say my &lsquo;opinion on the matter&rsquo; has been changed by
reading the essay and its accompanying summary by the author. The responses I
read were also very interesting. They were from seemingly center-left-wing
individuals like myself, only they were <em>not</em> persuaded by Graham&rsquo;s arguments.</p>

<p>My point here is not so much to discuss the piece, as the tone of the piece.
This piece was written with a tone that raises the hair on the back of the
necks of liberals. This may have been unintentional on the part of Graham,
&hellip;although considering the follow-up discussions of his previous piece on
females in tech, may he just likes raising those particular hairs (they&rsquo;re
called &ldquo;hackles&rdquo;).</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I will now summarize what I took from the essay. Technology increases the
potential productivity of people at an exponential rate. Since some people do
not become more productive, this correspondingly increases the <em>variability</em> of
productivity within the population. Those who are more productive in producing
innovative goods are benefitting society. They mainly only are interested in
being more productive <em>because</em> of the possibility of getting rich off of it.
If we want to help the poor, the problem is <em>not</em> that there are rich people;
the problem is that there are poor people. To help the poor, instead of taking
away the ability for the productive to get rich, we should help the poor become
more productive. This is because economic inequality <em>per se</em> is not the issue,
poverty is.</p>

<p>For me, this is, as I&rsquo;ve mentioned, both convincing and enlightening. But there
are two concerns any left-winger is almost certainly going to bring up. First,
a lot of people&rsquo;s wealth is not made by being productive in a way that benefits
society; shouldn&rsquo;t we wage class-war against them? Second, even people who
became rich by benefitting society, are likely to abuse their wealth via some
form of corruption, so that&rsquo;s why we should prevent them from getting rich in
the first place. After those two arguments, there are a few other popular
rebuttals. (E.g.) Third, why should we allow some people to be <em>that</em> much
richer than everyone else; something about it seems creepy, therefore it should
be prevented.</p>

<p>These <em>are</em> legitimate concerns, they just don&rsquo;t <em>actually</em> rebut anything
Graham was saying. That&rsquo;s why, if Graham wants to have a legitimate
conversation with people who are going to make the above rebuttals, his
argument should <em>start</em> by saying that those rebuttals are <em>correct</em>, and then
go into how it is <em>still</em> the case that his original arguments are correct. In
this way, the hackles are down, and the legitimate points can be heard.</p>

<p>However, maybe Graham wasn&rsquo;t writing the essay for left-wing people to be
convinced. Maybe he was trying to convince right-wing people. If that is true,
the essay was pointless, because right-wing people <em>already</em> agree with the
opinions he stated. Or maybe he was writing the essay for maximum &ldquo;virality&rdquo; to
increase his fame and international mindshare. In that case, I&rsquo;m not a good
judge of effective argument technique.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
