<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Networking | With Pith]]></title>
  <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/blog/categories/networking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-11T23:11:15-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ethanp.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ethan Petuchowski]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Basics of Wireless Communication]]></title>
    <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/09/07/basics-of-wireless-communication/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-07T17:45:58-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/09/07/basics-of-wireless-communication</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been doing the readings for my <a href="http://www.cs.utexas.edu/~lili/classes/F15-CS386W/">Wireless Networking course</a> at
UTexas, and in the process have dug into much of the basics of radios and
networks that I had ignored in the past. Here, I will try briefly describe what
I have learned. Maybe not everything I will say here is exactly correct, but I
think it&rsquo;s at least <em>mostly</em> correct.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s try to start somewhere near the beginning. Our <strong>goal</strong> is to transfer a
<em>information</em> from one location <code>LocSND</code> to another <code>LocRCV</code> <em>conveniently</em>.
The way we will accomplish that is by having <code>LocSND</code> manipulate the
<em>electromagnetic field</em> around <code>LocRCV</code>. More specifically, we will <em>encode</em> a
binary <em>dataframe</em> as <em>modulations</em> of a <em>radio signal</em> around a pre-determined
<em>carrier frequency</em>.</p>

<p>How do we <em>do</em> that?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>We use an LRC circuit to make electrons oscillate in an
antenna. These oscillating electrons ram into loose and excitable electrons in
the antenna&rsquo;s metal, this releases a photon at a particular frequency. Globally
(i.e. within the entire transmitting antenna), enough photons are being
released that it seems to an external observer looking at the produced
electromagnetic (EM) field like there is a continuous signal being emitted.</p>

<p>So we&rsquo;re sending these EM ripples, which are generally at our carrier
frequency. However, if we just sent a basic frequency, there would be no
<em>information</em> in there, so we have to <em>modulate</em> it. We can modulate its
amplitude (A), phase (phi), and frequency (omega), the 3 free
parameters of the equation (in the top left of the equation in the following
gif from &ldquo;sengpielaudio&rdquo;)</p>

<p><img src="http://www.sengpielaudio.com/Sinuskurve01.gif" alt="sine wave" /></p>

<p>This would give us
1. <strong>Carrier frequency</strong> &mdash;&ndash; the EM frequency <em>inside</em> which our signal is
  encoded
2. <strong>amplitude shift keying (ASK)</strong> &mdash; send signal at <em>carrier frequency</em> by
   modulating the signal&rsquo;s <em>amplitude</em>
3. <strong>frequency shift keying (FSK)</strong> &mdash; similar but modulates <em>frequency</em>
4. <strong>phase shift keying (PSK)</strong> &mdash; again, but modulates <em>phase</em></p>

<p>One simple method would be to say our carrier frequency is 5 Hz, but our band
is actually [4,6] Hz. So whenever the signal is 4 Hz, that means I&rsquo;m sending a
0, and if the signal is 6 Hz, it means I&rsquo;m sending a 1, and a new digit starts
every 1 ms. That would be an example of <strong>FSK</strong>.</p>

<p>A fundamental problem that we must solve is that all senders and receivers of
information via EM fields with their antenna(s) are sharing the a single
<em>medium</em> for transmitting that field (viz. the air, etc.). So if <code>LocSND</code> sends
a message to <code>LocRCV_1</code>, then <code>LocRCV_2</code> sitting one foot away can hear that
message loud and clear. This leads to three major issues: <strong>security</strong>,
<strong>multiplexing</strong>, and <strong>interference</strong>.</p>

<p>To <strong>multiplex</strong> means to send multiple distinct signals through a single
channel. How are we going to send distinct signals to receivers 1 and 2 in such
a way that both can understand the signal meant for them? We can chop up the
frequency band that our transmitter can use into 2 smaller bands, and use each
of those bands as separate carriers. Then we tune the receivers to pick up
frequencies in their respective bands. This is what is called <strong>frequency
division multiplexing (FDM)</strong>, but we can also multiplex across space, time,
and <em>code</em>.</p>

<p>Of course, I&rsquo;ve only scratched the very surface of what&rsquo;s going on here, but
that&rsquo;s all the time I&rsquo;ve got.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Akamai Does]]></title>
    <link href="http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/06/10/what-akamai-does/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-10T21:23:31-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ethanp.github.io/blog/2015/06/10/what-akamai-does</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I met someone at a hack night worked for Akamai. He was a cool dude, so I was
curious what Akamai does. For whatever reason I ended up reading a paper cited
as so:</p>

<blockquote><p>Nygren, Erik, Ramesh K. Sitaraman, and Jennifer Sun. “The akamai network: a
platform for high-performance internet applications.” ACM SIGOPS Operating
Systems Review 44.3 (2010): 2–19.</p></blockquote>

<p>For whatever reason, everything I know about Akamai is from this paper. I&rsquo;m not
in any way afiliated with Akamai, etc., though the paper is basically a badly
designed advertising pamphlet for their services. A small number of sentences
in this summary may have been lifted directly from that paper. You can consider
this whole post a paraphrasing of the paper. <strong>The intent of this post is to
tell you everything important that I learned from the paper</strong> in a form that is
<em>way</em> easier to digest than you reading the paper itself. To that end, this
document is maybe 2 pages long, and the original is 17. Clearly much of the
detail has been removed, but the gist remains. If that appeals to you, welcome
aboard! Note that the paper is from 2010, so is probably already out of date.</p>

<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>Akamai invented the <em>Content Delivery Network</em> (CDN) concept in the 1990s,
because the raw naive Internet implementation is too slow to conduct a global
business. As of 2010, Akamai delivers 15-20% of global Web traffic.</p>

<h3>The Interwebs is a dangerous place</h3>

<!-- more -->


<p>For a web app, downtime and high latency is <em>very</em> costly. Customers won&rsquo;t go
to your page unless they can see your content <em>right this second</em>. The Internet
itself can provide no reliability or performance gaurantees.</p>

<p>The Internet is composed of 1000s of individual networks, the largest having
only 5% of Internet access traffic. It takes 650 networks to get to 90% of all
access traffic. The Internet-access pricing structure happens to result in a
situation in which connections between networks (&ldquo;peering points&rdquo;) are
bottlenecks causing packet loss and increased latency.</p>

<p>The protocol ISPs use to exchange rounting information (BGP) is bad and subject
to misuse. Internet outages and partitions are regular occurrences. The strict
ACK policy for TCP adds enough overhead to make video streaming over TCP
impractical. The high proportion of people still using IE6 means any improved
algorithms that get implemented have to be backwards compatible with that one
silly browser.</p>

<h2>Content Delivery Networks</h2>

<p>Originally a CDN&rsquo;s purpose was to cache static site content at the &ldquo;edge&rdquo; of
the Internet, close to end users, to avoid middle-mile bottlenecks. Now they
accelerate entire web apps and provide HD live streaming media. They provide
security, logging, diagnostics, reporting, and management tools</p>

<p>A <strong>delivery network</strong> is a <em>virutal network</em>, i.e. a software layer over the
actual Internet, to provide reliability, performance, scalability, and
security. It requires no client software or changes to the underlying networks.
Akamai&rsquo;s network is made from tens of thousands of globally deployed servers
running sophisticated algorithms to enable faster content delivery.</p>

<h3>In Greater Detail</h3>

<p>When a user enters a URL into their browser, their DNS routes them to an Akamai
DNS, which in turn gives them the IP address of an <strong>edge server</strong> chosen via
machine learning algorithm. The edge server acts as a cache for the <strong>origin
server</strong>, and if it needs new data, it uses an especially reliable and
performant <strong>transport system</strong> (described later on), which is a network of
internal nodes who know best how to connect the <em>edge</em> back to the <em>origin</em>.</p>

<p>The <strong>transport system</strong> connects <em>edge</em> to <em>origin</em> servers with a cache
pyramid of clusters. Streaming video is <em>branched out</em> to the edge clusters by
intermediate layers of <em>reflectors</em>.</p>

<p>Edge servers communicate to each other via their own chosen path optimization
rather than the default one chosen by BGP, and use dynamically optimized TCP
parameters. They can also intelligently prefetch and cache content from the
origin right before before it is requested by the user.</p>

<p>Akamai&rsquo;s EdgeComputing product allows you to distribute your web application
<em>itself</em> &ldquo;to the <em>edge</em>&rdquo;, which is great for content aggregation, product
catalogs (dynamic access of static content), data validation, and data input
batching. It&rsquo;s not great for apps relying heavily on transactional databases
because they still must communicate with the origin server.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
